Inventory of the Germany (Territory under Allied occupation, 1945-1955: U.S. Zone) Office of Military Government miscellaneous records
Hoover Institution Archives
Germany (Territory under Allied occupation, 1945-1955: U.S. Zone) Office of Military Government miscellaneous records
1944-1950
80197
Germany (Territory under Allied occupation, 1945-1955: U.S. Zone) Office of Military Government.
14 manuscript boxes (5.6 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Correspondence, reports, memoranda, statistics, indexes, laws, proclamations, press releases, and bulletins, relating to American administration of occupied Germany after World War II, and especially to civilian relief, economic conditions, housing, and denazification.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1980.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Related Materials
Germany (Territory under Allied occupation, 1945-1955), Hoover Institution Archives
Germany (Territory under Allied occupation, 1945-1955: U.S. Zone) Office of Military Government for Bavaria. Kreis Traunstein, Hoover Institution Archives
Biographical/Historical Note
The Allied powers who defeated Nazi Germany in World War II divided the country west of the Oder-Neisse line into four occupation zones for administrative purposes during the period 1945-1949. The American zone consisted of Bavaria and Hessen in Southern Germany, and the northern portions of the present-day German state of Baden-Württemberg. The port cities of Bremen (on the Weser River) and Bremerhaven (at the meeting of the Weser and North Sea) were also placed under the control of the U.S. because of the American request to have toeholds in Northern Germany, as well as the bulk of the south. The city of Berlin was jointly occupied by the Allied powers and was itself subdivided into four sectors. The headquarters of the American military government was the former IG Farben Building, Frankfurt am Main.
Scope and Content of Collection
The records of American administration of occupied Germany (U.S. Zone) contain documentation mostly of the Office of Military Government, Berlin Sector (OMGBS) and the Office of Military Government, U.S. Zone (OMGUS), 1945-1949.
These records represent materials relating to civilian relief efforts, particularly economic conditions, housing, and denazification, and including correspondence, reports, memoranda, statistics, indexes, laws, proclamations, press releases, and bulletins. Information on living conditions and the food availability may be found in "Food Ration Entitlements and Ration Issue Report," 1945-1948, while historical reports on the housing situation and housing relief efforts are presented in the Building and Housing Section reports.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Denazification.; International relief.; Military government.; Reconstruction (1939-1951)--Germany.; World War, 1939-1945--Civilian relief.; Germany--History--1945-1955.
Collection Contents
- Indexes, 1944-1950 (Box 1-2)
  - "Catalogue of Intelligence Research Reports Available for Distribution within the Federal Government for Official Use," by the Office of Intelligence Research (OIR), 1948 (Folder 1: 1)
  - Information Bulletin, Magazine of U.S. Military Government in Germany, no. 160, 1949 (Folder 1: 2)
  - Information Control Review (Formerly Intelligence Summary), Office of Military Government for Germany (U.S.) (OMGUS), 1949 (Folder 1: 3)
  - "Intelligence Summaries," Headquarters of United States Forces in Austria, Office of the Director of Intelligence, 1945-1948 (Folder 1: 4)
  - International Military Tribunal, Office of the United States High Commissioner for Germany (Folder 1: 5)
  - Laender Laws of U.S. Zone, 1948 (Folder 1: 6)
  - Military Government Gazette, 1949 (Folder 1: 7)
  - Military Review, Command and General Staff College, Fort Leavenworth, Kansas, 1948-1949 (Folder 1: 8)
  - Newspapers and magazines, 1946-1949 (Folder 1: 9)
  - OMGUS Historical Branch microfilms, 1945-1948 (Folder 1: 10-11)
  - OMGUS publications, 1949 (Folder 1: 12)
  - OMGUS reports, 1949 (Folder 1: 13)
  - Organization plans, 1944-1948 (Folder 1: 14)
  - Proof readers' marks (Folder 1: 15)
  - Radio Bulletin, circa 1945 (Folder 1: 16)
  - U.S. Forces European Theatre (USFET) Headquarters, "Central File Index", 1945 (Folder 1: 17)
  - U.S. Group Control Consul for Germany (USGCC), Headquarters, Intelligence Section, Library, 1945 (Folder 1: 18)
  - War Department Pamphlet "Preservation and Use of Key Records in Germany", 1944 (Folder 1: 19)
  - Vital Speeches of the Day, semi-monthly journal, 1948 (Folder 1: 20)
  - 201 Index of Generals (Source: USFET Decimal File), 1945-1946 (Folder 1: 21-23)
  - Index cards, circa 1945 (Folder 1: 24, Folder 2: 1-3)
- Headquarters European Command Historical Division (EUCOM), 1947-1950 (Box 2-3)
  - "Weekly Report of Documents Received," nos. 455-588 with corrected copies, November 1947-April 1950 (Folder 2: 4-12)
  - Organizational Chart and Directory of Key Officers as of 1 July 1949 (Folder 3: 1)
- Office of Military Government, Berlin Sector (OMGBS), 1945-1950 (Box 3-9)
  - "Food Ration Entitlements and Ration Issue Report", 1945-1948 (Folder 3: 2-21)
  - Building and Housing Section, 1946-1950 (Folder 4-9)
    - Housing situation reports, 1946-1949 (Folder 4: 1-10)
    - Applications, 1946-1948 (Folder 4: 11-16)
    - Housing of National Sozialistische Deutsche Arbeiter Partei (NSDAP) members, 1946-1950 (Folder 5: 1-14)
    - Housing of NSDAP members, 1946-1950 (continued) (Folder 6: 1-3)
    - Correspondence re housing cases, 1946-1949 (Folder 6: 4-15)
    - Correspondence regarding housing cases, 1946-1949 (continued) (Folder 7: 1-12)
    - Financial reports on custodians of NDSAP properties in The American Sector of Berlin, 1947-1948 (Folder 7: 13-17)
    - Financial reports on custodians of NDSAP properties in The American Sector of Berlin (continued), 1947-1948 (Folder 8: 1-12)
    - Financial reports on custodians of NDSAP properties in The American Sector of Berlin (continued), 1947-1948 (Folder 9: 1-3)
- Office of Military Government, U.S. Zone (OMGUS), 1945-1949 (Box 9-13: 1-3)
  - Public Welfare Branch, 1947-1949 (Folder 9-12)
    - Weekly reports from districts on relief applications, 1948-1949 (Folder 9: 4-13)
    - Monthly summaries from main welfare office, 1947-1949 (Folder 9: 14-19)
    - Public Safety Branch, Internal Affairs and Communcations Division, reports on denazifications, 1945-1946 (Folder 10: 1-7)
    - Public Information Office, releases, 1947-1949 (Folder 10: 8-14)
    - Public Information Office, releases, 1947-1949 (continued) (Folder 11: 1-7)
    - Press Branch, Information Service Division, weekly newspaper analysis, 1949 (Folder 11: 8)
  - Office of Military Governor, 1947-1949 (Folder 11-12)
    - Military Government Law and regulations, memoranda, 1947-1949 (Folder 11: 9-14)
    - Special reports, 1947 (Folder 11: 15)
    - "Communications (Quarterly Review)", 1949 (Folder 11: 16)
    - "Monthly Report of the Military Governor," nos. 43 and 48, 1949 (Folder 12: 1-2)
    - "Statistical Annex," nos. 43 and 48, 1949 (Folder 12: 3)
  - Reports, 1946-1949 (Folder 12)
    - "Military Government Legislation", 1946-1949 (Folder 12: 4-6)
    - Monthly OMG (Office of Military Government) Report for December 1947 (Folder 12: 7)
    - "Monthly Report of Public Safety Statistics," by Civil Administration Division, Population and Analysis Branch, 1948 (Folder 12: 8)
    - "Governmental Organization in the Occupied Zones of Germany," by Civil Administration Division, 1947 (Folder 12: 9)
    - "Declassification of Reports," by Field Information Agency, Technical (FIAT), Records Branch, 1946 (Folder 12: 10)
    - "Land and Local Government in the U.S. Zone of Germany: Appendix, Charts of Typical Government Agencies," special report, 1946 (Folder 12: 11)
    - Status Report on Military Government of Germany U.S. Zone, 1946 (Folder 12: 12)
    - Weekly Information Bulletin, Military Government, Office of the Director, no. 27, 1946 (Folder 12: 13)
    - "German Militarism: A Study of Militaristic Tendencies in Germany Today as Revealed by the Attitudes of Opinion Leaders," special report No. 7, 12 February 1948 (Folder 12: 14)
    - Military Government Gazette, published by OMGUS, 1947 (Folder 12: 15)
    - News of Germany, summary compiled by Press Control Branch, Information Control Division, Vol. 3 and 4, 1949 (Folder 12: 16)
    - "Memorandum for the Press" relating to currency reform and taxation, Department of the Army, Public Information Division, Press Section, 1948 (Folder 12: 17)
  - Manpower Division, Visiting Expert Series, 1949 (Folder 13: 1-4)
    - "Labor Organization in German Public Administration and Services," by Joseph Mire (Folder 13: 1)
    - "Employers' Associations in Western Germany," by D.F. MacDonald (Folder 13: 2)
    - "A Message from Dutch Trade Unionists to German Labor," by H.J. Meijer, R. Laan, and H. Koppens (Folder 13: 3)
    - Weekly Information Bulletin, Control Office, no. 106, 18 August 1949 (Folder 13: 4)
- Staatliche Erfassungs-Gesellschaft Für Offentliches Gut m.b.H. (STEG), Economics Branch, Industry Section, 1947-1949 (Box 13: 4)
  - Smelting program, 1947-1949 (Folder 13: 5)
  - Policy and directives to OMGUS, 1947-1948 (Folder 13: 6-9)
  - Receipts and data of distribution of surplus U.S. Army stocks by OMGBS, 1947-1948 (Folder 13: 10-12)
- Supreme Headquarters Allied Expenditionary Force (SHAEF), 1945 (Box 14: 10-12)
  - Production Control Agency Industrial Investigation reports, plants 38-102, 1945 (Folder 14)
- Miscellany, 1945-1949 (Box 14: 1-8)
  - "Acquisition List for Maps of Foreign Areas," by Central Intelligence Agency, 1949 (Folder 14: 9)
  - "American Policy in Occupied Area," The Department of State, United States Government Printing Office Washington, D.C., 1947 (Folder 14: 10)
  - Photographs of sorted art work, prepared to assist in the recovery of art (14 prints), 1944-1945 (Folder 14: 11-12)